<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The power and glory of the Lord shining out of the north, or The day of the Lord dawning: wherein the true light is holden forth to all who desire to walk in the day. With a warning to the people of England of all sorts, not to oppose Christ in his kingdom. Shewing also the way how all flesh comes to know the Lord and fear him, by his terrible shaking the earthly part in man, witnessed by the holy men of God in Scripture. With a word to the serpents seed, or ministers of Antichrist, or man of sin, wherever he is found. By one whom the Lord hath called out of this dark world, into the true light, whom Ismaels brood calls a Quaker, whose name in the flesh is James Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E711_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207117</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118452</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E711[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The power and glory of the Lord shining out of the north, or The day of the Lord dawning: wherein the true light is holden forth to all who desire to walk in the day. With a warning to the people of England of all sorts, not to oppose Christ in his kingdom. Shewing also the way how all flesh comes to know the Lord and fear him, by his terrible shaking the earthly part in man, witnessed by the holy men of God in Scripture. With a word to the serpents seed, or ministers of Antichrist, or man of sin, wherever he is found. By one whom the Lord hath called out of this dark world, into the true light, whom Ismaels brood calls a Quaker, whose name in the flesh is James Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the sign of the Black-spred-Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August ye 17:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118452:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Power and Glory of the LORD Shining out of the NORTH, OR THE <hi>Day of the LORD Dawning:</hi> WHEREIN The true Light is holden forth to all who deſire to walk in the Day.</p>
            <p>With a Warning to the People of <hi>England</hi> of all ſorts, not to oppoſe Chriſt in his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Shewing alſo the way how all fleſh comes to know the Lord and fear him, by his terrible ſhaking the earthly part in man, witneſſed by the holy men of God in Scripture.</p>
            <p>With a Word to the Serpents Seed, or Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, or Man of Sin, wherever he is found.</p>
            <p>By one whom the Lord hath called out of this dark World, into the True Light, whom <hi>Iſmaels</hi> brood calls a Quaker, whoſe name in the fleſh is <hi>James Nayler.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Then ſpake Jeſus again unto them, ſaying, I am the light of the world; he that followeth me ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life,</hi> 
               <bibl>Joh. 8. 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Therefore behold I will proceed to do a marvellous work among this people, even a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous work and a wonder; for the wiſdom of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of their prudent men ſhall be bid,</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa 29. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>For in my jealouſie and the fire of my wrath have I ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken, ſurely in that day there ſhall be a great ſhaking in the Land of Iſrael, ſo that the fiſhes of the Sea, and the fowls of the heavens, and the beaſts of the field, and all creeping things that creep upon the earth, and all the men that are upon the face of the earth ſhall ſhake at my preſence, and the mountains ſhall be thrown down, and the ſteep places ſhall fall, and every wall ſhall fall to the ground,</hi> 
               <bibl>Ezek. 38. 19, 20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the ſign of the Black-ſpred-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118452:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118452:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Power and glory of the Lord ſhining out of the North.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL People everywhere who profeſs that you love God, and have a deſire to walk in his<note place="margin">Rev. 11. 8.</note> ways, and are in this dark world wandering too and fro, enquiring the way how you may come out of this great City, which is <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hineſs and darkneſs rules, and is heard, wherein the Lord is crucified, and all the righteous blood hath been ſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and your ſelves are kept in bondage to ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, blindneſs and thick darkneſs, and know not where you are, nor the way out of this condition, though many of you have been inquiring after the way ſo many years, ſeeking after your blinde guides, who are not the way, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the way themſelves, and ſo have forſaken the fountain of light, and have run after, and have been led by them who are in the ſame darkneſs with you, now ſtand ſtill a while and ſee where you are, and what you have been doing; you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as to the Kingdom of God, but you are not ſeeking where it is; you have been ſeeking without, but it is within you, and there you muſt find it, if ever you finde it, it is not to be found in Forms and Cuſtoms, and outſide Obſervations;<note place="margin">Luk. 17. 21.</note> but the Kingdom of God is within you, and the way to the Kingdom is within you, and the light that guides into the way and keeps in the way is within. Chriſt is the way, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118452:3"/>
know ye not that Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates?<note place="margin">Joh 14. 6.</note> and as he is the Way, ſo he is the Light; I am the light of the<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note> world, and lighten every one that cometh into the world;<note place="margin">Joh. 1. 9. and 8. 12.</note> he that followeth me ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life. I am the true ſhepherd of the ſheep, and my ſheep know my voice, but the voice of a ſtranger they<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 19.</note> will not hear, and the voice of Chriſt is ſpiritual &amp; not carnal,<note place="margin">Rev. 2. 7, 17.</note> and he ſpeaks to the Spirits in priſon, and he that hath an ear<note place="margin">Joh. 10. 11, 12.</note> hears whats the Spirit ſaith; and he who comes once to hear the voice of Chriſt in Spirit, will no more deſire to hear the voice of ſtrangers. All your hirelings are ſtrangers to Chriſt, and he knows them not; for though they may propheſie in his name, and in his name caſt out devils, yet if they be workers<note place="margin">Mat. 7. 22, 23.</note> of iniquitie, Chriſt knows them not, and ſuch know not Chriſt; <hi>For he that ſaith I know him, and keeps not his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>is a lyer.</hi> Now all people, ceaſe from your ſtrange guides, and outſide-lights, and return to the light of Chriſt in you, that which ſhews you ſin and evil, and the deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for what ever makes manifeſt is light, and this is that light which ſhines into the conſcience, which tells you that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 13.</note> ſwearing, pride, envy, coveteouſneſs, backbiting and diſſembling leads to condemnation, and this light checks you for ſin, and would have you to do to all men, as you would be done to. And this light is not a Chapter without you, in a Book, but it is that light that revealed that to the Saints in their ſeveral meaſures, which they ſpoke forth, and which thou readeſt in the Chapter; and this light being minded will lead to the perfect day, which declares all things as they are. And this did the Apoſtles exhort the Saints everywhere to take heed unto till the day dawned, and the day-ſtar did ariſe<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 19.</note> in their hearts, and this is a more ſure word of propheſie then that the Apoſtle did ſee in the mount, as he declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and if you take heed to this light to obey and love it, then it will ſhew that to you which no outward declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man can ſhew you; it will let you ſee all your ſins done in ſecret, and whom you have wronged, and how you have ſpent your time, and will bring you to repentance and to tenderneſs of heart towards all people, and will bring you to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118452:3"/>
exerciſe a pure conſcience in the fear of God, towards God<note place="margin">Act. 24. 16.</note> and man in uprightneſs, and ſo will lead up to Juſtification and Peace; and if you diſobey it, it will condemn you in your own hearts, and will ſhew you that God is greater then your hearts, who will render to every one according to their works; and here you are left without excuſe before God, Men and Angels; and in this, that you know ſin and live in it, here you have learned your codemnation, and your deceit is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, whereby with a pretence you make prayers, and ſay, Lord ſhew us a ſight of our ſins, when as God hath given you a light within you, which being minded and obeyed, will ſhew you all your ſins and wickedneſſes, and lead you out of them;<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 20.</note> but this light you hate, becauſe you love your evil deeds; and you periſh, not for want of light tendred, but becauſe you turn your backs on it; for when you ſhould bring your works to it to be proved, then you joyn with the deceit to make co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers for your ſins, and hide them leſt they ſhould come to the light, and be made manifeſt; and this is the cauſe why you ſtumble, becauſe you walk not in the light, for your evil deeds will not abide the light; the Adulterer loves the night, and<note place="margin">Iob 24. 15. and 16.</note> the thief loves the night, and the drunkard loves the night, and all the children of darkneſs love the night, that they may<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 7.</note> bring forth their evil deeds unreproved.</p>
               <p>And here thou art who loveſt thy ſins, and here wilt thou be found, profeſs what thou wilt; for the day will throughly declare thee what thou art; for now is the day of the Lord which will judge thee as thou art, neer at hand, and wo to thee that hideſt thy ſins, and covereſt chine iniquities; thou maiſt hide it from men, and make men believe thou art a Chriſtian, but God will not be mocked; for above all, he abhors the<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8.</note> hypocrite and diſſembler; wherefore take heed and turn from your deceit, and come forth you children of darkneſs, and come into the light, where there is no occaſion of ſtumbling, and make it appear you are children of the light, by loving it; and make it appear you love the light, by bringing your deeds to it to be proved, that all your works may be works of the light, that your light may ſhine forth before all men in your works, and that true Judgment may be ſet up in you, and all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118452:4"/>
condemned and caſt out, and truth received in, that the truth may make you free: for while you joyn with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 32, 34.</note> you conſent to keep your ſins, and while you commit ſin you are the ſervants of ſin, and the wages of ſin is death, and death reigns in you, becauſe you will not come to Chriſt, who<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 19.</note> is the light, that you may have life, and your deſtruction is of your ſelves, and God is juſt, and your condemnation is this, that light is come into the world, and you love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe your deeds are evil, and this is that grace of God, that hath appeared to all men, which is the Saints Teacher, and teacheth them to deny-ungodlineſs and<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> worldly luſts, which you that live in your luſts turn into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, and will not be taught by it, and here you read your<note place="margin">Iude 4.</note> condemnation in every ſin you commit.</p>
               <p>O you people of <hi>England!</hi> how long will it be ere you be obedient to the Kingdom of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt!</hi> how long will you profeſs him in words and forms, and yet will not own him in power! you can be content to let him have the name of a<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 20.</note> King, ſo that you your ſelves may raign, and under the name of Chriſts Kingdom act your own wills; and though you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<note place="margin">Tit. 1. 16.</note> bear it to be Judged by the Spirit of Chriſt where it is in his people, which judgeth all the world, and all things; yet<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 15.</note> you cannot eſcape; for you ſhall be found guilty before the mighty Judge of Heaven and Earth, when he ſhall appear in flames of fire to be avenged upon all deceipt and unrighteouſneſs of men: And will you be found at that day<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note> Subjects in the Kingdom of Chriſt wherein all the Saints are one, and Chriſt their head and Law-giver? or are you not Lords over Gods heritage, yea over Chriſt himſelf? and you will appear ſuch when the myſterie of iniquity ſhall be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Mat. 28. 20.</note> in you; you who ought to make it your whole care to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Law of Chriſt in all things that he commands, as a Rule for you to walk by; but are you in your duty as ſervants to Chriſt, when you are preſcribing him ways to walk by in his Church? And is it not ſo, when you would limit him to ſpeak only by ſuch as you in your wiſdom approve of, or elſe he ſhall be ſilent? and to effect this are all the powers of the earth combined together; do not you here take upon you to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118452:4"/>
be Lords of the vineyard, and not ſervants, and would not<note place="margin">Mat. 21. 23. to the end.</note> ſuffer him to ſend forth Labourers into it, who is Lord of it? Is not this the way to make the heritage your own? hath not all the perſecutions of the meſſengers of God ariſen from this ground? And how many times have earthly powers been<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36. 16.</note> broken to pieces againſt this Rock? And do you walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures, which you ſay is your rule, when you would limit the Spirit of the Lord, not to ſpeak in his own time, and in what place ſoever they who have the meſſage are<note place="margin">Amos 7. 13.</note> ſent into? you who are offended becauſe the Lord ſends his Meſſengers into your Idol Temples, to cry againſt your Idol<note place="margin">Act. 5. 19, 20</note> worſhips, and Heatheniſh cuſtoms, and to call out poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people from amongſt you, which have been long decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note place="margin">Act. 17. 2, 3.</note> by their blind guides: And to call them out of forms and likeneſſes, into the ſubſtance of all worſhips, which is only in Spirit, and not in Forms and Cuſtoms, and outſide obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 21, 22, 23, 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> that they may come to know what they worſhip, even the living God, that their ſouls may live, which was the way by which the Apoſtles did gather the Saints out of all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols Temples and Carnal worſhips into the Spirit, as you may read in the Scripture: And this (with you) is a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of your Law, and you ſay it breeds diſtraction in your Churches; but what Churches are they which will be ſo ſoon diſtracted? and what people are thoſe Churches made up of, who no ſooner hear one deliver the Lords Meſſage in a peaceable way, but they are all on fire, beating, buffetting, curſing, ſwearing, and haling them to priſon? and were you not blind, you might plainly ſee what generation theſe are, who are, and always have been offended at the will of God. Is it not the love of God to ſouls to ſend to call them who will hear his voice, out of ſuch Churches as are thus acted by a Spirit of envy, rage and murther, which is the ſpirit of the Devil? and this is that Spirit which being offended, ſets the Creatures one to deſtroy another, leaſt his deceipt ſhould be revealed; and are you not blinde who cannot diſtinguiſh of that ſpirit which acts in the perſecutor, and that Spirit which acts in the ſufferer, and hath ſo done in all Ages, and come out from amongſt them? And what Law is that which you ſay is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118452:5"/>
tranſgreſſed by the creature, being obedient to the Creator, obeying the voice of Chriſt witneſſed in the Scripture by the practiſe of the holy men of God, ſent out by the ſame Spirit into the world, as theſe are at this day? Is this a Chriſtian Law, as you pretend it to be, that thus withſtands Chriſt in his Kingdom? and were you ſpiritual, as you pretend, would not theſe carnal Laws that oppoſe the Spirit and practiſe of the<note place="margin">Acts 17. 2, 3.</note> Saints, be laid aſide by you? and now try whether that Spirit act in you, which led the Apoſtles and Saints into the Temple and Synagogues daily, there to diſpute againſt all Idolatrous worſhips, and to hold out to the people the true ſubſtance, and thereby gathered the Church into God, in the Spirit, there to meet and worſhip; or that Spirit that was in them who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted<note place="margin">Acts 16. 19, 20, 21.</note> the Saints for ſo doing, and commanded them ſilence, and charged them with breaking their Law, and turning the world upſide down, and counted them mad men: And if any be moved to ſpeak a word of truth while your Pariſh Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are talking, or before their glaſs be run, you that execute a carnal Law upon the bodies of ſuch, are you ſubject to the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is in the Spirits of his own, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he rules the conſcience, and brings them to obey him in his commands? Or will not you be found in the day of tryal to be fighters againſt him, under the name of profeſſing him?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 30.</note> And do theſe whom you perſecute, any thing but what was the Saints practiſe? And how are you not aſhamed to profeſs that Scripture to be your Rule, which ſaith, If any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, let the firſt hold his peace; and this the Apoſtle ſets down as order, and the Saints liberty; but what Spirit acts you, who would reſtrain it, and call it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hale them before Rulers, or to priſon for ſo doing? And you that ſay If ſuch have their own liberty, it is reaſon they ſhould be ſilent, and not cry out againſt others, know that the Law of Chriſt is not grounded on the will and reaſon of men; And is your reaſon here any thing but carnal? for doth pure reaſon give any way that deceit ſhould go under the name of truth unreproved? and is there any reaſon to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Spirit of Chriſt that it ſhall not diſcover the man of ſin wherever he is, who muſt be deſtroyed and revealed by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118452:5"/>
brightneſs of his coming in his Saints, and by the ſword of his mouth? and is there any reaſon that the powers of the earth ſhould make Laws for the Spirit of Chriſt in the Saints to act by (though in all Ages they would be medling with it to their own hurt?) And if all ſhould be ſubject to your Law, which you ſay is reaſon, how ſhould truth be ſpred abroad, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit be brought to bluſh, ſeeing deceit hath always, and doth ſtill wind into the earthly powers; for ſafety? but truth ſeeks no corners not ſhelters from earthly powers; for all that ever was ſent out by Chriſt to preach the Goſpel, was called by him alone, without the conſent of earthly powers; neither ſtood they to the judgment or Tryal of any men or powers, as from them to receive order whether to preach or forbear, but by his authority alone by whom they were ſent, to whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone they were to give accompt of their Miniſtry, with joy or ſorrow; and in this work they denyed all the Learning and Wiſdom of the World; Chriſt was not learned, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles was not learned; and <hi>Paul</hi> when he tells of his bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Acts 4. 13.</note> up in learning, counts it amongſt other (carnal) things, loſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> droſs and dung (which before he had counted gain) that<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 7, 8.</note> in the loſs of them he might win Chriſt. And ſaith, that the knowledge of the Goſpel, he had it not of man, nor by man, nor was he taught it, but by the revelation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but what Rule walk you by, who muſt have them to ſuch a<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 11, 12</note> pitch of Learning, and ſo many years at <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and then to ſtudy ſo long in Books and old Authors? and all this is to know what unlearned men, Fiſher-men, Plow-men &amp; Herdſ-men did mean when they ſpoke forth the Scriptures, who were counted fools and madmen by the learned gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration when they ſpoke it forth; And they who ſpeak it by the ſame Spirit, are ſo ſtill by the ſame Serpents wiſdom; And when you have brought them to this height of Learning; yet the Scripture is a book ſealed to all their wiſdom and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">Rev. 5. 3.</note> and they from whom you expect the opening of this myſterie are at a jar amongſt themſelves, what ſhould be the meaning of it; and have been in all Ages diſputing, quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, impriſoning, killing and burning one another, and would do ſo now, had they power; for this learned generation have been the ſtirrers up of all ſtrife and bloodſhed, ſetting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118452:6"/>
Nations and People one againſt another, and all about ſtanding to uphold their Meanings, Forms and Imaginations and vain conceptions from the Letter, but are all ignorant of that Spirit which gave it forth; for they who have the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, contend not about words and meanings, and that Spirit is the ſubſtance which gave it forth and opens it again, as it ariſeth in its meaſure; and they who have that Spirit are Miniſters of the Spirit, and they miniſter to the raiſing up of the Spirit in others, and not to the Serpents wiſdom; for they know that wiſdom which ſtands in the will of man muſt not enter; for the myſterie is hid from it, and ſuch cannot perſecute the bodies of men becauſe they know not ſo much as they, neither do they ſeek to deſtroy the Creature, but they ſtrike at the accurſed Spirit, which keeps the Creature in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and bondage, and ſo redeems the Creature and reconciles him to God in the Spirit, and this is the Miniſtry of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, guided by the Spirit, and by this was the Scripture written forth; for holy men of God ſpoke forth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1 12,</note> as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, without car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal learning; and holy men by the ſame Spirit read and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them again, not by carnal learning and natural tongues; for the Spirit is the Original, which firſt reveals the myſterie to<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> the Spirit within man, and then declares it forth in words or<note place="margin">Eph. 3. 3, 5.</note> writing to the underſtanding of others, to the directing their minds to wait upon God for the ſame free-gift of the Spirit, &amp; here is the true worſhip in Spirit found and performed, which ſtands in the teaching of the Spirit, and not in the Letter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the world, but owned of God; but all you who ſeek to find out the inviſible things of God, or the way of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note place="margin">Mat, 11. 25.</note> by your learning and wiſdom in the letter, you ſeek that which is hid from your wiſdoms, &amp; you take the Saints conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to talk on: And they having outwardly declared their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip and fellowſhip they had with God in Spirit, and<note place="margin">1 Ioh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 3.</note> this you find in the Letter, and every one according to your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral conceivings thereof, ſets up an outward form, image, or likeneſs of the Saints worſhip, and here you worſhip, and for this you contend by reaſons and arguments, and wreſt the<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 16.</note> Scriprures to uphold your form; and if any will not worſhip this your Image, you are greatly offended; and here is all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118452:6"/>
contention in the world about things without, as forms, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and traditions; and here carnal minds contend with<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 6, 7.</note> carnal words and weapons about carnal things; and you who are here cannot own the Saints conditions in your ſelves, as to witneſs the infallible teachings of the Spirit, and the body of ſin put off, and to be ſanctified throughout in ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but you will own the Scriptures (as they are) as far as they will make with your Form, and that you may live in the delights of the world; And for thoſe which croſſe your ways and wills, you will alter them by meanings and expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thus the Scripture muſt bend to you, and ſubmit to your wills, that the will may raign, and you live in your luſts; but to believe that ever they ſhalbe fulfilled in you by Chriſt, as<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 3, 4.</note> they are and were in the Saints, to this your Faith is reprobate: And yet you are not aſhamed to profeſs Chriſt your King, and the Scripture your Rule, and you make a great ſound in words, the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the Ordinances of Chriſt, and the Church of Chriſt, and the Saints practiſe, and the Scripture Rule; but is it ſo upon tryal, or but a thing like theſe you ſpeak on? and where you appear to be wanting, there you have covered with words meanings and expoſitions; but the Saints whoſe conditions you talk on, was what they ſpoke without meanings or deceit: they were ſubjects in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and he did rule in them, and they followed<note place="margin">Rev<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14.</note> him through perſecution, mockings and death; but is it ſo with you, who are Lords over your brethren, beating, mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, impriſoning and killing them, becauſe they will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the commands of Chriſt to be ſubject to your wills, and heatheniſh cuſtoms, as to bow down to you and worſhip you, and to be ſilent at your will, and to ſpeak at your wills though Chriſt command the contrary? Is this to own Chriſt for your King? And as for your Ordinances you cry up ſo much, are theſe they to ſet up a proud man called by you<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 6. 10.</note> maſter, having the higheſt place in the Idols Temple, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always from a verſe of another mans condition, but not fulfilled in himſelf, raiſing points, reaſons objections and uſes, a divination of his own brain, but not from the mouth of the Lord, adding and diminiſhing to the Scripture, ſprinkling of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118452:7"/>
infants, and calling it baptizing into Chriſt, ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> conditions in Rimes, telling People of a Sacrament, and<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 10, 11.</note> obſerving of times, doing all for Tythes or money, living in pride, fulneſs and coveteouſneſs, and many more like things, never uſed by any that ever Chriſt ſent? And is this your Church, all within ſuch a place or Pariſh, ſprinkled when they were infants, but not yet waſhed from ſin, but are ſtill lyars, ſwearers, drunkards, whoremongers, covetous, ſcorners, proud, wanton, oppreſſors, and ſuch like, but not one that can witneſs that faith which hath overcome the world, ſin and the devil, or believes that ever they ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5. 4.</note> while they are here? and is this the Church of Chriſt, which is his body, which are limbs of the devil, and ſerve him at his will? And is this the Saints practiſe you ſpeak of, to exalt your ſelves one above another, to ſue one another, to accuſe falſly, to be proud and covetous, to live in the luſts<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 26, 27.</note> of the fleſh, ſporting and gaming, and calling it recreation, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in exceſs of apparel and diet, ſpending the creatures on<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 24.</note> your luſts, when your brethren want food and raiment, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing others to labour in wants, that they may bring it to you to ſpend on your luſts and vanity? And when you ſhould hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the light of Chriſt in your conſcience, then you joyn with the deceit to make covers for your iniquities, and ſay it is but as your place and eſtate requires, as though God had given out his Law with reſpect of perſons, and had given you<note place="margin">Jam. 5. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> a toleration to abuſe the creature, and live in your luſts more then others, becauſe you have more of the earth, or a greater power committed to your charge amongſt men then others,<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 25, 26, 27.</note> not conſidering that the Heathen exerciſe theſe things; but the Saints, the greater power, the more humble, and the more<note place="margin">Luk. 22. 26.</note> carefull to walk as examples to others, that ſo they may exalt him alone whoſe Miniſters they are, and not themſelves in pride; and this is to be truly honorable, and herein have all the faithfull been honoured; but you who ſeek for the worlds honour are not of the faithfull; for ſaith Chriſt, how can you believe that ſeek for honour one of another? now you<note place="margin">Joh. 5. 41. 44.</note> that talk of the Saints practiſe, own it in your ſelves, and it will take you off from theſe and many more vanities you live
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118452:7"/>
in; God will not be mocked; you hypocrites, be not ſayers, but doers. And you talk of the Scripture being a golden Rule, but your ways prove, how little you are ruled by it; Do ye ſeek to be perfect? for God is perfect; holy as he is holy? do ye love God above all and your neighbours as your ſelf, when you make them your footſtool? do you to all as you would be done by; have you forſaken the world and the love of it? Is the luſts and affections of your fleſh crucified? having<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5.</note> food and rayment, are ye therewith content? Do you live<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 8, 9.</note> by faith, not taking thought for tomorrow, not what to eat<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 25. to the end.</note> and what to put on? Do you live as the Lords Lilies? Do you feed the hungry and cloath the naked, and let the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note place="margin">Iam. 2. 1, 9.</note> go free? Are ye no reſpecters of perſons in all your deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Are you brought to yea and nay in all your communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 37.</note>, without any more which comes of evil? Do you ſuffer<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 11.</note> and are hated, and have all manner of evil ſpoken on you falſly for the name of Chriſt? Are you brought out of all the<note place="margin">Luk. 6. 22.</note> cuſtoms of the heathen, and are conformable to Chriſt in his life and ſufferings? prove your ſelves if you be what you profeſs in truth, that you be Saints, ſanctified and redeemed out of all worldly and earthly things, to live to God in all things, in righteouſneſs and holineſs: Oh you take but their conditions to talk on, which was ſo; and ſo you boaſt in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans line on things that are not your own. See if you be made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt, as they were, and<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 12.</note> if you know him, whom you ſay you worſhip, to dwell in your<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16.</note> bodies, as they did, and that you are taught of him in Spirit how he will be worſhipped, as they were whom you talk on. See whether theſe things be ſo in ſubſtance, or you have but a form of their worſhip, gathered out of the letter, and ſo you worſhip a likeneſs or image of that whereof they had the ſubſtance: now if you have but the outſide, take heed; for now is the hand of the Lord upon all the Idols of the world;<note place="margin">Zach. 13. 2.</note> and that which is not the ſubſtance is but an image; and now ſhall the ſtone cut out of the mountain without hands, break<note place="margin">Dan. 2. 34.</note> thee and thy image in pieces, and he that is without form ſhall by his power, break all your Forms and formal Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips<note place="margin">Rev. 14. 9.</note> in pieces, and that worſhip alone ſhall be ſet up, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118452:8"/>
is in ſpirit, and not in form, and is accepted by that God who never was known in form, but in ſpirit, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever.</p>
               <p>And you Rulers of the Nation, take heed how you ſtep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the throne of Chriſt, or exalt your ſelves in his Kingdom, and mind what power you are betruſted with by the Lord, and be faithfull in that, as the Miniſters of God to whom you are<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23. 3.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 56. 1.</note> to accompt; you are to puniſh ſin in whom it is, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 14.</note> of perſons: And if you be faithfull herein, you will find<note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 3, 3, 4.</note> work enough in the Nation: And you are to encourage them that do well, and deliver them from the power of cruel and<note place="margin">Prov. 29. 2.</note> blood-thirſty men that oppreſs them; for he that departs from iniquity is made a prey to this generation: and you are<note place="margin">Iſa. 59. 15.</note> to walk as examples to the people, in all holineſs and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that God may bleſs you and honour you in the doing of his commands: but as for ſending out Labourers into his Vineyard, where hath he commanded this at your hands, or when did he in any Age reprove any for not doing it? He hath overthrown Kingdoms and Nations for abuſing, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">2 Chron 36. 15, 16.</note> about to ſtop the mouths of thoſe that he ſent, and hath reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, Touch them not; but theſe were ſuch as he ſent; for he never betruſted the powers of the earth to chooſe him meſſengers to go on his meſſage:<note place="margin">Luk. 10. 2.</note> And hath he now put power into your hand, that you ſhould not ſuffer him to chooſe his own meſſengers, by whom he will ſend to his own people? And have you the meſſage to put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mouths, and muſt they go on your errand or his? and will not you give Him leave to chooſe his own ſervants, and what he will imploy them about? will you deal ſo with him, as you would not have any to deal with you? And for your Tythes, Augmentations, and ſet benefits, when did ever God require any ſuch thing from any Magiſtrates under the Goſpel? and doth it ſerve for any other end, but to hold up an idle, loytering Miniſtry, one pulling another out of places, and ſetting themſelves in their ſtead, that they may heap up riches and live in their luſts, all running greedily after the wages of<note place="margin">Zach. 11. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Balaam</hi> for gifts and rewards? And do you fear that the hand of God is ſhortened, that he will not raiſe up ſuch as will go<note place="margin">Ezek. 22, 25.</note>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118452:8"/>
on his meſſage, unleſs you provide them wages? Did ever<note place="margin">Iſa. 50. 2, 4.</note> any that he ſent complain to the world for want? nay, all my Fathers ſervants have bread enough, without being cared for by the world; for thoſe who are ſent by Chriſt, take little care for ſuch earthly things, having a better reward, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable riches? And can you ever keep the Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt out of places (who will conform to any thing for gain) ſo long as they can have you to feed them with money? And will not you be found guilty of keeping up the hirelings that the wo is to, and them that hold them up, and whom Chriſt is come to diſcover and caſt out, and ſo you be found fighters againſt him? And when you leave all that ſay they are Chriſts Miniſters to Chriſts maintenance ſet down in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, then it will appear who have run unſent, and have not profited the people; And is it not the love of God to caſt out ſuch as have called themſelves Teachers, and have been thus long in places, and have their people yet lyars, ſwearers,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 7. 18.</note> drunkards, proud and covetous, and in all filthineſs, but not one that is ſet free from ſin and brought out of the world, and they who have taught them dare not truſt them for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, without a Law to compel them? And are you doing any acceptable ſervice to God in maintaining ſuch as theſe as they live? And will it not be ſaid to you one day, who requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe things at your hands, to oppreſs the poor who labour<note place="margin">Prov. 22. 16.</note> hard to give their labours to maintain theſe belly-gods (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their conſcience) in their fulneſs, pride and luſt, and their wives and families in idleneſs; and they that labour for it, are many times in great want?</p>
               <p>Oh be wiſe and take heed what you do; and as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves to be a Chriſtian Magiſtracy, ſo minde the commands of Chriſt, and not your own wills; it is not ſaying you are Chriſtians, but walking after Chriſt and his commands, that differs you from heathen: And do not profeſs the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in words, but own their practiſe that gave them forth; and let them who ſay they are Miniſters, make proof of their Miniſtry in power, and not in getting a few words whereby to deceive you and the people, but let them firſt ſow ſpiritual things before they reap carnal; firſt beget a people out of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118452:9"/>
world into the Spirit, and then they ſhall not need to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 11.</note> with them about food and rayment, nor ſue them at the Law; firſt plant, then eat; And this was the practiſe of ſuch as Chriſt ſent, and he always provided them a houſe to go to<note place="margin">Acts 4. 34.</note> who were worthy, and meat to eat, and they never wanted what was good for them; and I witneſs that he is the ſame now, and hath the ſame care over thoſe that he ſends into the world, with divers others whom he hath ſent out without bag or ſcrip, yea into the moſt brutiſh parts in the Nation; praiſes, praiſes be to our God, whoſe is the earth and the fulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 25.</note> and thus we do witneſs the Scripture fulfilled, and take no thought for food and raiment as the heathen do, but are come into the unity with all Saints in their joy and ſufferings,<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 11, 12.</note> and are taught by Chriſt how to want and how to abound, and in all conditions to be therewithall content; and we can truly ſay all is for good to us, and to the Church of Chriſt: And our Kingdom and joy is not of this world, nor doth the<note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 22.</note> world know us, nor our joy; glory to the higheſt for ever, who is ſhaking all the wiſdoms and powers of men, to eſtabliſh that which is of himſelf alone, to which all ſhall be made to bend and bow.</p>
               <p>And you that are in power, minde the promiſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at the coming of Chriſt to his Kingdom, <hi>I will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, overturn, overturn, till it come into his hand whoſe right it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>is, and upon his ſhoulders ſhall the government be eſtabliſhed (he that hath an ear to hear let him hear</hi>) And take notice how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have been overturned already, who would have been limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him by their wiſdoms: And now it is come into your hands, who above all have ſeen his wonders done for you and<note place="margin">Amos 3. 2.</note> the Nation, and you above all have declared that you deſire is that Chriſt alone may reign in his Kingdom, and ſome of you I have known to be tender towards any who looked that way. Oh that there were ſuch a heart in you, to lay aſide all your own wills and carnal conſultations, and to take Counſell<note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 1.</note> at the Spirit of the Lord, and be guided by his pure light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into your conſcience, which would bring you into the fear of the Lord, and to depart from ſelf-ends, intereſts and exaltations, and to follow rhe Law of God in eſtabliſhing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118452:9"/>
Laws for your ſelves and others to walk by, and that you may follow the practiſe of the Saints left in Scripture, without<note place="margin">Pſal. 89 14, 15, 16.</note> wreſting it, that ſo you might come to have unity with them in the ſame Spirit that gave them forth, and ſo be guided by the ſame Spirit of Juſtice and Judgment, by which all were guided that ever have ruled well in all Ages, whom God did bleſs and hath honoured for ever; that ſo God may bleſs you, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh you, and preſerve the Nation out of the hands of yours and the Nations enemies. And that you may be honoured<note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 23.</note> with taking away oppreſſion, and wicked and unjuſt Rulers,<note place="margin">Zach. 7. 9. to the end.</note> who are the cauſe of it, who judge not the cauſe of the poor and needy, and which the Lord hath been grieved at theſe many years; but if you forget your ſelves, and what you have promiſed before the Lord in the day when you ſought unto him for deliverance, and ſo exalt your ſelves over the poor, and ſet up your own Laws, and not the Law of God in its pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, I declare unto you this day, from the Word of the<note place="margin">Iſa. 42. 23.</note> Lord, that he will overturn you, and raiſe up his Kingdom<note place="margin">Iſa. 14. 26, 27.</note> another way; whether you will hear, or whether you will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, the word of the Lord ſhall ſtand; for the Almighty God<note place="margin">Hag. 2. 6, 7.</note> hath been ſhaking the Nations, that his glory may appear, and there ſhall be no reſt, untill his Kingdom be eſtabliſhed above all mountains. Hear all ye powers of the earth, The Lord alone will raign.</p>
               <closer>This I am to declare abroad, that they who are wiſe-hearted may underſtand and fear before the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; the time is at hand; he that Believes ſhall be Eſtabliſhed.
<signed>James Nayler.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118452:10"/>
               <p>TAke heed how you ſpeak evil of the things you know not, <hi>Jude</hi> 10. You who neither know the Lord, nor his works in your ſelves, take heed how you judge it in others; you are without God who are in the world, and the works of God have always been ſtrange to that Nature which you live in; but ſearch the Scriptures, and you ſhall finde that the holy men of God do witneſs quaking and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and roaring and weeping, and faſting and tears; but the world knows not the Saints conditions. But beware there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſt that come upon you which is ſpoken of in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, of ſuch deſpiſers and ſcorners as you are. <hi>Behold, ye deſpiſers, and wonder, and periſh; for I work a work in your days, a work which you ſhall not in any wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you,</hi> Acts 13. 40, 41. <hi>The Lord reigneth, let the people tremble; he ſitteth between the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims, let the earth be moved,</hi> Pſal. 99. 1. <hi>Tremble thou earth at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of the God of</hi> Jacob, Pſal 114. <hi>My fleſh trembleth becauſe of thee, and I am afraid of thy judgments,</hi> Pſal. 119. 120. <hi>He looketh upon the earth, and it trembled; he toucheth the hills, and they ſmoke,</hi> Pſal. 104. 30. <hi>A fire goeth before his face, and burneth up all his enemies round about; his lightning enlightened the world; the earth ſaw and trembled; the hills melted like wax at the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 97 3, 4, 5. <hi>Fearfulneſs and trembling are come upon me, and horrour hath overwhelmed me,</hi> Pſal 55 5. <hi>So terrible was the voice, that</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid, I exceedingly fear and tremble: whoſe voice then ſhook the earth; but now he hath ſaid, that once more I ſhake not the earth only, but heaven alſo,</hi> Heb. 12. 21, 26. When <hi>Paul</hi> heard the voice of Chriſt, he trembling
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118452:10"/>
and aſtoniſhed, ſaid, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> Acts 9. 6. The Corinthians received <hi>Titus</hi> in obedience, with fear and trembling, 2 <hi>Cor. 7. 15. Paul</hi> was with the Corinthians in weakneſs, and fear, &amp; much trembling, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 3. When <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned of righteouſneſs, temperance &amp; judgement to come, <hi>Felix</hi> trembled, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 25. The Apoſtle exhorts the Saints to work out their ſalvation with fear &amp; trembling, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12. The Jaylor when he believed, he came trembling, and fell down before <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Act.</hi> 16. 29. When <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed his ſons, he trembled very exceedingly, <hi>Gen. 27, 33. Hear the word of the Lord, ye that tremble at his word: your brethren that hated you, that caſt you out for my names ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified; but he ſhall appear to your joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed.</hi> Iſa. 66. 5. Thus ſaith the Lord, to this man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart, and trembleth at my words, <hi>Iſa. 66. 2. Oh that thou wouldſt rent the Heavens, that the mountains might flow down at thy preſence; as when the melting fire cauſeth the water to boyl, and to make his name known to his adverſaries, that the Nations may tremble at his preſence,</hi> Iſa. 64. 1, 2. <hi>Yea, I will make many people amazed at thee, and their kings ſhall be hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly afraid for thee, when I ſhall brandiſh my ſword before them, and they ſhall tremble at every moment, every man for his own life, in the day of thy fall,</hi> Ezek. 32. 10. When <hi>Habakkuk</hi> heard the voice, his belly trembled, his lips quivered, and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs entred into his bones, and he trembled in himſelf, that he might reſt in the day of trouble, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 16. When <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw the viſion, he ſtood trembling, &amp; they that were with him thought that they ſaw it not, yet a great quaking fell upon them, ſo that they fled to hide themſelves, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. 7 11. When God ſets up his Son as King, all are exhorted to ſerve him with fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and rejoyce with trembling, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2 6, 11. When <hi>Iob</hi> remembred God, he was afraid, and trembling took hold on his fleſh, <hi>Iob</hi> 21. 6. The pillars of heaven tremble, and are aſtoniſhed at his preſence, <hi>Iob 36. 11. Which ſhaketh the earth out of her place, the pillars thereof tremble,</hi> Job 9. 6. <hi>Thou haſt made us to drink the wine of aſtoniſhment, thou haſt made the earth to tremble, thou haſt broken it, heal the breaches
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118452:11"/>
thereof, for it ſheketh,</hi> Pſal. 60. 2, 3. <hi>The earth ſhook, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens alſo dropped at the preſence of the God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Pſal. 68. 8. And the Land ſhall tremble and ſorrow; for every purpoſe of the Lord ſhall be perſormed againſt Babylon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Jer. 51. 29. When <hi>Ezra</hi> heard of the peoples ſins, he pluckt his hair off his head, and off his beard; he rent his garment, and ſate down aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; and there aſſembled unto him all that trembled at the word of the God of <hi>Iſrael, Ezra</hi> 9. 3, 4. The people were to enter into Covenant with God, by the counſel of thoſe that trembled at the Command of God, <hi>Ezra 10. 3. The Lord will take the cup of trembling out of the hands of his people, and put it into the hands of thoſe that afflict them,</hi> Iſa. 51. 22, 23. When the Lord ſhall roar, then the Children ſhall tremble as a bird, <hi>Hoſ. 11. 10, 11. Shall not the Land tremble for this, and every one mourn that awelleth therein? and all feaſts ſhall be turned into mourning, and all ſongs into lamentation, as a lamentation for an only ſon,</hi> Amos 8. 8, 10. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts. Yet a little while, and I will ſhake the Heavens, the Earth, the Sea, and the dry Land; and I will ſhake all nations, and the deſire of all nations ſhall come, and I will fill my houſe with glory, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Hag. 2. 6, 7. <hi>I beheld the Mountains, and lo they trembled, and all the hills moved lightly,</hi> Jer. 4. 24. <hi>At his wrath the earth ſhall tremble, and the Nations ſhall not be able to abide his indignation,</hi> Jer. 10. 10. <hi>Tremble ye women that are at eaſe, be troubled ye careleſs ones, ſtrip ye and make ye bare, and gird ſackcloth upon your loyns,</hi> Iſa. 32. 11. <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaid, his heart was broken within him, all his bones ſhaked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Lord, and becauſe of the word of his Holineſs, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23 9. The Elders of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> trembled at the coming of <hi>Samuel, 1 Sam. 16. 4. Ezekiel</hi> was commanded to eat his bread with quaking, and drink his water with trembling and with carefulneſs, <hi>Ezek. 12. 18. Blow the trumpet in Zion, ſound an alarme in my holy mountain; let all the inhabitants of the Land tremble; for the day of the Lord cometh; for it is nigh at hand,</hi> Joel 2. 1 <hi>For in my jealouſie, and in the fire of my wrath, have I ſpoken; ſurely in that day there ſhall be a great ſhaking in the Land of Iſrael, ſo that the fiſhes of the Sea, and the fowls of the Heaven, and the Beaſts of the field, and all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118452:11"/>
creeping things that creep upon the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all the men that are upon the face of the earth ſhall ſhake at my preſence, and the mountains ſhall be thrown down, and the ſteep places ſhall fall, and every wall ſhall fall to the ground,</hi> Ezek. 38. 19, 20. When God heard <hi>Davids</hi> prayer out of his holy Temple, the earth ſhook and trembled, the foundations of the hills moved, and were ſhaken becauſe he was wroth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 6, 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> roared all the day long, and was weary with his<note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 8.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 3.</note> groanings; he wept all the night, and made his bed to ſwim<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 6.</note> with tears; he faſted till his knees grew ſeeble, and his fleſh<note place="margin">Pſal. 109. 24.</note> failed of fatneſs, untill he could number his bones, while he<note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 6, 7, 17.</note> ſuffered the terrors of God; he was diſtracted, he was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach<note place="margin">Pſal. 88. 15.</note> among men for ſo doing, and deſpiſed of the people;<note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 16.</note> all that ſaw him laught him to ſcorn, he was a mocking to the<note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 16.</note> wicked, they made mouths at him, and ſhaked the head at him;<note place="margin">Pſal. 41. 6.</note> the drunkards made ſongs of him; he was a taunt and a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word<note place="margin">Pſal. 71. 7.</note> among them; dogs compaſſed him about; the aſſemblies of wicked men incloſed him; vain perſons came to ſee him, that they might tell it abroad, and he was a wonder to many, and a ſtranger to his brethren, and his kinſmen ſtood afar off.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, We have heard a voice of trembling, of fear, and not of peace. Ask now, and ſee whether a man doth travel with childe; wherefore do I ſee every man with his hands on his loyns, as a woman in travel? and all faces are turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to paleneſs. Alas, for that day is great, ſo that none is like it; it is even the time of Jacobs trouble, but he ſhall be ſaved out of it,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Jer. 30. 5, 6, 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Hear now this ye fooliſh people, and without underſtanding, which have eyes and ſee not, which have ears and hear not; fear ye not me, ſaith the Lord? will ye not tromble at my preſence?</hi> 
                     <bibl>Jer. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, 22.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118452:12"/>
               <head>A Word to the Seed of the Serpent, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Antichriſt, or Man of Sin, wherever he is found.</head>
               <p>KNow this thou ſubtil One, who haſt long upholden a Kingdom of ſin, unrighteouſneſs, injuſtice and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, with all manner of filthineſs by thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that now the day of thy torment is at hand; for now is that ſeed ariſen, which is appointed to diſcover thee and thy deceitfull workings, and to bruiſe thy head, and to lay all thy pride and glory in the duſt: And he will ſet up a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<note place="margin">Iſa. 29. 14, 15</note> of righteouſneſs, purity and holineſs in the hearts of his people, who have been deceived through thy divination and witchcrafts theſe many years. And you Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, who have made people believe that you were the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of Righteouſneſs, by your crying out againſt ſin in words, and making poor ignorant people think that you were enemies to all unrighteouſneſs, and lovers of purity and perfection; but now that the Lord is bringing out a people out of the unrighteous world, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body of ſin, and bringing them up to righteouſneſs, holineſs and perfection, even to the Image of his dear Son, in which they were created, and ſo to himſelf again, from whence they were fallen by ſin, and could no other way be reſtored, but by being made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. which God having begun to effect, now you are forced to uncover and ſhew your ſelves, whoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters you are, and what Kingdom you ſtand for, with all your power oppoſing the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is in holineſs<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 4.</note> and perfection: And now you are forced (leaſt the man of ſin ſhould fall) to tell the ſame people to whom you have been all this while talking againſt ſin, impurity and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that they muſt never look while they are here to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118452:12"/>
ſin, the world, and the devil, nor ever come to purity and perfection; and thus you labour to keep a hold for the man of ſin as long as people live, and ſo perſwade them to leave the work of redemption and freedom till after death, or you know not when, and thus encourage people to ſpend their days in folly, and leave the world with torment and horror at their death.</p>
               <p>Now it being that you are ignorant of that pure light of the Spirit that convinceth thoſe who will own it, I am moved from the letter, for the ſimple ones ſake, who have been long deceived by you, to give ſome diſcoveries to your ſelves and all who will ſee whoſe Miniſters you are, and for whoſe Kingdom you Miniſter.</p>
               <p>And firſt, You that ſay none can be free from ſin while they are here, you are Miniſters againſt the truth, <hi>John</hi> 8. 32, 34.</p>
               <p>Secondly, You are againſt that which the Father promiſed at the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 1. 21. Ioh. 1. 29. Ier.</hi> 50. 20.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, You are againſt the end for which Chriſt came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, <hi>Joh</hi> 8. 34, 36.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, You are againſt the end of Chriſts ſufferings, <hi>Gal. 1. 4. 1 Pet. 3. 18. Rom. 4. 25. Rom. 6. 10, 11. 2 Cor. 5. 21. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, You are againſt the end of Chriſt being manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Saints, <hi>Rom. 8. 3, 4. 1 Joh. 3. 8. 1 Ioh.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, You are againſt that which manifeſts the children of God from the children of the Devil, 1 <hi>Ioh. 3. 10. 1 Ioh.</hi> 5. 18.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, You are againſt the commands of God and Chriſt, <hi>Iſa. 52. 11. Joh. 8. 11. 1 Tim 1. 5. Ioh.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
               <p>Eightly, You are againſt that which the Saints did witneſs wrought in them by Chriſt, <hi>Rom. 6. 1, 6, 7, 18, 22. Rev. 1. 5. 1 Pet. 2. 24. 1 Joh. 3. 6. 1 Joh. 5. 18. Col.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
               <p>And you that ſay none can come to holineſs and perfection while they are here; and to prove this you take the Saints conditions which they declared as they were paſſing on in growth toward it: and hence you go about by your ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to make People believe that they never did attain to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and all this, leſt any ſhould preſs after it, as though God did command his People to labour for that which is not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118452:13"/>
to be attained. And now judge if you were not blind whom you miniſter for, and whom you are againſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, You are againſt the End for which Chriſt offered up himſelf. <hi>Heb. 10. 14. Tit.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
               <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>condly, You are againſt the Commands of God, <hi>Mat. 5. 48. 1 Pet 1. 16. Levit. 11. 44. Deut. 18. 13. Levit. 20. 7. Gen.</hi> 17. 1.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, You are againſt the End for which Chriſt comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Saints. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 23.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, You are againſt the End for which Chriſt begifted and ſent out all his Miniſters into the World, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, You are againſt the work of the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to whom they writ and taught. <hi>Jam. 1. 4. 2 Cor.</hi> 7. 1. &amp; 13. 11. 1 <hi>Chron. 28. 9. Heb.</hi> 6. 1.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, You are againſt that which the Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt laboured and prayed for to be wrought in the Saints, night and day. 1 <hi>Theſſ. 3. 10. Col. 1. 28. Heb. 13. 20, 21. 1 Pet. 5. 10. Col.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, You are againſt the End for which the Scriptures are written. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, You are againſt the teſtimony God himſelf bears of his own, <hi>Gen. 6. 9. Job 1. 8. Job</hi> 2. 3.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, You are againſt what the Saints witneſs to be in themſelves and others, 2 <hi>Kin. 20. 3. Phil. 3. 15. 1 Cor. 2. 6. 2 Cor. 12. 9. Pro. 2. 21. Pro. 11. 5. Pſal. 37. 37. Pſal. 64. 4. Pſal. 101. 2, 6. Heb. 12. 23. 1 Ioh. 3. 3. 1 Ioh.</hi> 4 17.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, You are againſt that, without which God and man can never be reconciled in one again, <hi>Heb. 7. 19. Hab. 1, 13. Dan. 9. 24. 2 Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 21. 1 Cor. 3. 17. Mat. 5 8. Pſal. 15. Prov. 15. 9. 29. Pſal.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
               <p>And now let them who are wiſe-hearted, judge whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters you are, that are thus againſt God, and the recovery of loſt man into his firſt eſtate, and ſee if it be not the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that acts you thus in ſubtilty to keep man in the Fall, by which the fall of man was occaſioned at the firſt; and let all judge whether you be the Miniſters of righteouſneſs, or of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; of Chriſt the King of purity and peace, or of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118452:13"/>
Antichriſt, the Prince of this World and man of ſin, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; now by your fruits you are known and ſhall be judged; wherefore repent and ceaſe limiting the Lord, and meaſuring the pure Spirit of God in his people, whom he hath called out of the world, and ſanctified thereby un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fruits of righteouſneſs, obedience, holineſs and perfection; And meaſure not this with that ſpirit of pride, coveteouſneſs, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and envy, and perſecution which rules in you, who are yet in the world, and the love of it, which is enmity with God, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. 4. But ſee within your ſelves what is the cauſe why you are ſuch enemies to righteouſneſs and perfection; you are too rich in your ſelves, in your own wiſdom, by your earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom, to wait for the good and perfect gifts of God from above, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 17. You envious ones, you want the bond of perfectneſs, which is charity, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 14. You hypocrites, who hear, and ſay, and do not that which leads to it; how can you come to perfection, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 22, 23, 24, 25. You are too much in words, but too little in practiſe to come to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for Faith is made perfect through works, and not through words, <hi>Iam. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22. 1 Cor.</hi> 4. 20.</p>
               <p>And you fat worldlings, who live in pride, pleaſure and fulneſs, and have your hearts in the earth; ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 14. and there Chriſt tells you the plain cauſe why you bring no fruit to perfection: now wo unto you who have ſet your ſelves in places to lead people up to God out of the Fall, ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs; but now when the Lord is come, none are found ſuch oppoſers of purity as you are; O repent, how long will it be ere you ceaſe to pervert the ways of God for your own ends? Oh that you had eyes to ſee, that you might make peace with him, leaſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.</p>
               <p>ANd now to you poor ſcattered ſheep, who have been ſcattered by theſe hirelings, in this cloudy, dark day, which hath been upon all fleſh ſpred upon the face of the earth, and you have been running from mountain to hill, to find the Lord, but have not found him, who is to give reſt to your ſouls: And many of you are ſtill wandring you know
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118452:14"/>
not where: Others have ſeated themſelves under green trees, and are worſhipping you know not what, but as others tell you, who know as little of the true and living God as your ſelves; Others are weary with ſeeking where nothing can be found, and are fallen aſleep in the world of eaſe and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: others have their ears open to all voices, which cry, lo here, lo there, but know not who to truſt, being all in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; now all awake to meet the Lord, who is ariſen to ſeek and ſave, and gather into one fold all his ſcattered ones, and to bring them up to <hi>Zion</hi> the holy City, where he will feed them himſelf alone, without fear, in good paſture, where they ſhall lie down in peace; now come off from all your blinde guides, that are not in the way themſelves; nor can they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect others where the way is; come out of the world and worldly cares and pleaſures, and return to the Lord in Spirit, he is within you, and there if you wait in Spirit you ſhall hear him ſpeak to your ſpirits, to the directing your minds out of all the works of darkneſs and ſin, up to God, where no ſin is, nor unclean thing can come, and if you minde to obey his voice, he will teach you to lay aſide all your diſſembling hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, whereby you have deceived your ſelves and others, profeſsing godlineſs in words, but denying it in power, and you will finde power given in from the Lord, to become what you profeſs in reality and truth, and to profeſs no more but what you are, that God may have glory by you, and take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in you; for this is the day of your viſitation, if you will own it; the day of Salvation from all ſin and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the day wherein all the children of the Lord ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be their peace, in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall they be eſtabliſhed, and they ſhall be far from oppreſſion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. 13, 14. Many of you have had great travel and gone through many ſorrows to finde reſt, but have found none; many prayers and tears, but no anſwer of peace; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days of ſeeking, but have not found him whom your ſouls thirſt after; and all this becauſe you have been ſeeking the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving among the dead; he is not to be found in the world, nor formal worſhips, nor in humane wiſdom and learning; but he is only to be found as he reveals himſelf freely, to thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118452:14"/>
who patiently wait for him in ſpirit. Dear People, to you that love the Lord above all earthly things, and yet have not your minds directed where to wait for him, to you I ſpeak to your ſouls that lie in death till they hear the voice of the Son of God; he is near you, who is the way to the Father, look not out, he is within you; that which I know, declare I unto you, and the way I know, where I have found my beloved, my Saviour, my Redeemer, my Husband, my Maker, who hath ſet me above all the world, my ſins, my fears, my ſorrows, my tears, into his love, to live with him in Spirit for ever; but dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily to all viſible things, praiſes, praiſes to my Father for ever. The night is far ſpent, the day is at hand, come out of darkneſs all that love the Lord, into his marvellous light, where you ſhall ſee what you have been, and what you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from, that you may live and praiſe the Lord; for it is the living that praiſe the Lord, and not the dead: Ariſe, come out of death, come away, and let us rejoyce together in his love, in the life of our king, even ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And you that are ſo much offended at perfection, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cleanſed from ſin, I leave theſe Queries with you to conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether any unperfect one, committing ſin, be the Image of God, yea or no?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether any can witneſs the work of Redemption com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in them by Chriſt, while they commit ſin, and are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the temptation of the Devil, yea or no?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether any unperfect and unclean one that lives in ſin, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, yea or no? and if not, how ſhall one dying in ſin; and where ſhall he be made perfect and clean, ſeeing the tree muſt lie as it falls; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you own a Purgatory, yea or no?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether a Chriſtian have ground to believe, that he may be recovered by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> into that eſtate in which he was created, and which he loſt in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> yea or no?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether God created man and woman perfect, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, and able in his power ſo to have ſtood, if they had not forſaken his power, and conſented to the wiſdom of the Serpent, yea or no?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118452:15"/>6. Whether God and man be wholly reconciled, till man be brought into that eſtate again, yea, or no?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether all thoſe that both by their life and doctrine labour to perſwade people to abide in that condition of ſin, imperfection and ſeparation from God (which Chriſt came to deſtroy, and ſo to unite man to God again) be not Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and for the upholding of the Kingdom of the Devil, yea or no?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118452:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
